Coolidge, John, 1913-1995. Papers, 1939-1984: A Guide
Papers, 1939-1984
Harvard Art Museum Archives, Harvard University
HC 15
Coolidge, John, 1913-1995
10 file boxes, 1 half-file box + oversize materials
These papers of former Fogg Art Museum Director and Harvard University Professor John Coolidge document a portion of his teaching activities, museum administration, and other personal and professional endeavors and interests. The papers consist primarily of personal correspondence, and date largely from 1947-1975. Also included are research materials, teaching materials, lecture notes, speeches, reports, resumes, photographs and financial records.
The papers were left at the Fogg Art Museum by former director and professor John Coolidge.
Conditions on Access
Access to most of the papers is unrestricted. Access to files containing information on personnel matters, student academic records and other materials deemed confidential is restricted. These restrictions are noted at the file level.
Copyright: The President and Fellows of Harvard University hold any copyright in Coolidge's papers. Copyright in some papers in the collection may be held by their authors, or the authors' heirs or assigns. Researchers must obtain the written permission of the holder(s) of copyright and the Curator of Archives at the Harvard Art Museum before publishing quotations from any material in the collection.
Related Material
There are additional papers of John Coolidge in the Harvard Art Museum Archives and the Harvard University Archives.
Biography:
John Phillips Coolidge was born in Cambridge, Massachusetts in December 1913, on either the 15th or 16th day; his parents disagreed about the exact date of his birth. His father, Julian Lowell Coolidge, was a professor of mathematics at Harvard and the first master of Lowell House, and his mother, Theresa Reynolds Coolidge, was a linguist. One of his uncles, Archibald Cary Coolidge, was a history professor at Harvard and also the first director of the Harvard University Library. Coolidge had one brother and four sisters. Following family tradition, he studied at Harvard as an undergraduate and received a B.A. in 1935. He married Mary Elizabeth "Polly" Welch the same year; they would have one child, Mary-Elizabeth "Penny" Coolidge Warren. Following graduation, Coolidge moved to New York to study architecture at Columbia University, but after a year of study decided he did not have the requisite talent to succeed as an architect and instead took up the study of art and architectural history. In 1936 he enrolled in graduate school at New York University, where he studied under German émigré scholars Erwin Panofsky,; Karl Lehmann,; Richard Krautheimer and Walter Friedlaender. He also taught at Vassar College from 1937 to 1939. Coolidge received an A.M. in 1939 and published a book based on his research for the degree in 1942: Mill and Mansion: A Study of Architecture and Society in Lowell, Massachusetts, 1820-1865. The book is still widely considered a classic social and economic history of American architecture and urbanism. Coolidge was also one of the co-founders in 1940 of the Society of Architectural Historians and served on the society's board of directors and as its first vice-president.
By 1940, Coolidge's academic focus had shifted to Italian Renaissance architecture. He wrote his doctoral dissertation on sixteenth century architect and theorist Jacopo da Vignola. The Second World War interrupted his academic work, however, and he entered the Navy as an ensign in 1943. He was stationed in Washington, D.C. and near London, working in communications until his discharge in 1946. He returned to academic work that year, teaching art history at the University of Pennsylvania for academic year 1946-1947. In the fall of 1947, Coolidge accepted a position at Harvard as assistant professor of architectural history; his dissertation was completed and accepted the same year. In 1948, at age 34, he was named director of the Fogg Museum and associate professor of art history. He was promoted to full professor in 1955 and served as director of the museum for twenty years, until 1968. Coolidge was involved in a range of ambitious endeavors at the Fogg: the museum's collections of Islamic and contemporary art were greatly strengthened during his tenure, and Coolidge encouraged students to organize exhibitions of modern and contemporary art and to write publishable catalogues for those exhibitions. He also continued his predecessors' work training future curators and other museum professionals through a program known as the Museum Course. Coolidge retired in 1968, took a sabbatical year, and returned to teach at Harvard in academic year 1969-1970. He continued teaching until 1984.
In addition to his work at Harvard, Coolidge was active as a trustee of the Boston Museum of Fine Arts from 1948 until 1974; he served as that institution's President from 1973 to 1975. He was also an active member of the Society of New England Antiquities. He was appointed Bingham Professor at the University of Louisville in 1985 and Samuel H. Kress Professor at the National Gallery of Art's Center for Advanced Study in Visual Arts for the academic year 1991-1992. Coolidge published numerous articles on American and Italian architecture and Baroque sculpture while he was at Harvard and published two books in his retirement, Patrons and Architects: Designing Art Museums in the Twentieth Century in 1989 and Gustave Doré's London in 1994. John Coolidge died in Boston, Massachusetts on July 31, 1995.
Arrangement
The collections is arranged in reverse chronological order at the folder level. Contents of folders have not been arranged by the processor.
Series I. Teaching Materials
Subseries A. Museum Course Curriculum Review
Subseries B. Museum Course & Teaching Materials
Series II. Speeches
Series III. Personal Papers
Subseries A. Personal Correspondence
Subseries B. Fogg
Subseries C. Writings
Subseries D. Organizations
Subseries E. Projects
Scope and Content:
The collection consists of a combination of museum and university records and personal correspondence. The papers date from 1939 to 1984, with the bulk of the materials falling between 1947 and 1975. Many of these materials coincide with John Coolidge's tenure as museum director spanning from1948 to 1968.
The collection is divided into three series "Teaching Materials," "Speeches" and "Personal Papers." The first two series consist primarily of official university and museum related records and correspondence. The third series may be broadly defined as personal papers, however there are instances of the inclusion of professional papers. As the majority of the files were found in reverse-chronological order, this arrangement has been maintained or imposed by the processor in an effort to provide greater accessibility to researchers.
The collection has been re-housed in archival folders and containers. Folder contents have been kept in their original order and folder titles have been retained, with any added information enclosed in square brackets by the processor. Over-stuffed folders have been divided into several folders and numbered sequentially to indicate that they represent part of a larger whole (for example: folder "1 of 2"). Oversize materials have been removed from their original folder locations for storage in an oversize cabinet. Separation sheets have been inserted in their stead to indicate their removal. These oversize materials may be consulted upon request; their location is indicated in the detailed container list that follows. Restricted materials removed from file folders have also been supplanted with separation sheets. The removal of these materials is also indicated at the file level in the container list below.
The papers are largely considered to be an artificial collection, gathered together by former museum staff merely on the basis of having been made or received by John Coolidge. The folders do not appear to be organized in the original order in which they were used or maintained by Coolidge. Nevertheless, folders have been preserved in the found order whenever possible. Folders clearly misfiled or in disarray have been re-arranged in an order deemed to be closer to the original file organization.
At some earlier date, the collection was divided topically by the insertion of labeled, file drawer "dividers." These dividers were used to separate the collection into discrete sections. These sections are now represented by separate subseries or groupings, evident in the finding aid's structure. For instance, Series III, Personal Papers, is divided into five separate Subseries, A through E, which range from "Personal Correspondence" to "Projects."
Some materials in the collection were damaged by a flood in the 1990s. This damage has rendered a limited number of handwritten documents unreadable, due to ink bleeding. In addition, some materials have adhered together as a result of this submersion. These materials may be treated by the conservation department on an as needed basis, per researcher request.
- Teaching Materials, I.
  Scope and Content:
  Series I consists primarily of papers related to the museum course. Subseries A, Museum Course Curriculum Review, consists of correspondence related to a re-evaluation of the museum course. This curriculum review was instigated by the July 1948 retirement of Paul J. Sachs, former Fogg Museum Associate Director and Harvard Fine Arts Professor. With the aid of then-Associate Professor, Jakob Rosenberg, Sachs had led Fine Arts 19Aa and 19Ab: Seminar in Museum Work and Museum Problems, until 1947. In 1948 Jakob Rosenberg, Charles Kuhn and John Coolidge formed a committee to consider how to proceed in Sachs' absence. The outline of a museum training program was produced and opinions sought from museum directors, curators and staff nationwide, including Andrew Ritchie,; Fiske Kimball,; Martin Weinberger and others. Additional suggestions were received from Gordon B. Washburn,; Rhode Island School of Design;; Huntington Cairns,; National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC; Paul J. Sachs and Marcel Aubert, of the Louvre, among others. With the advice of fellow museum professionals and museum course alumni (including Henri Dorra,; William H. Gerdts, Nesta and Walter Spink,; Cornelius C. Vermeule,; Carroll E. Hogan,; William Hutton,; Peter A. Wick and Lillian and Richard Randall), Coolidge, Kuhn and Rosenberg devised FA 201: Introduction to Museum Work and Museum Problems, which was offered for the first time during the 1949-1950 academic year.
  Subseries B. consists of materials related to the teaching and organization of the museum course. Coolidge taught the museum course and led course-related field trips during his tenure as museum director, 1948-1968, and Fine Arts faculty member, 1947-1984. The museum course made regular field trips to Washington, DC, Merion, PA, Philadelphia, PA, Baltimore, MD, Winterthur, DE, New York City, NY and Brooklyn, NY, as well as, institutions closer to home in Hartford, CT, New Haven, CT, Providence, RI, Worcester, MA, Springfield, MA, Andover, MA, Lincoln, MA and Boston, MA. During these excursions they were hosted by academics, museum directors, curators and staff, including Rudolf Berliner,; Adelyn Breeskin,; William Campbell,; W. G. Constable,; Perry Cott,; Charles Cunningham,; William Dooley,; Dows Dunham,; George Edgell,; David Finley,; Bartlett Hays, Jr.,; Chester Jewell,; Fiske Kimball,; Edward King,; David Little,; Henri Marceau,; John Maxon,; Thomas Messer,; Lamont Moore,; Charles Montgomery,; James Plaut,; John Pope,; Perry Rathbone,; Roland Redmond,; Andrew Ritchie,; Frederick Robinson,; James Rorimer,; George Stout,; Francis Henry Taylor,; John Thacher,; John Walker,; Frederick Walkey,; Bradford Washburn,; Archibald Wenley,; W. J. Young and many others. Coolidge also introduced his classes to patrons, critics and collectors, such as, Dorothy Adlow,; Ilse Bischoff,; Stephen C. Clark,; Joseph H. Hazen,; Henry P. McIlhenny,; Duncan Phillips,; Donald S. Stralem,; Justin K. Thannhauser and Irwin Untermyer. On other excursions they met dealers, including Durlacher Brothers,; F. Kleinberger & Company,; Jacques Seligmann & Co., Inc.,; Julius Weitzner,; M. Knoedler & Company,; Saidenberg Gallery and Wildenstein & Co.
  Records for the FA 201 museum course include field trip itineraries, hotel reservations and course schedules and assignments. The collection also contains correspondence and memos with museum directors, curators, staff, trustees, private collectors, patrons, critics, academics and dealers regarding museum course field trips and the arrangement of visiting speakers.
  In addition to the records concerning Fine Arts 201, a significant portion of the folders in the 1965-1981 group are related to a circa 1971-1972 course, entitled, FA 101: Introduction to Museums. The course was held at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts under the auspices of the Museum Seminar Program and included undergraduate and graduate students from Boston University,; Brandeis, Harvard, Radcliffe and Wellesley.
  Museum course and teaching materials of later origin, 1965-1981, were originally filed in their own sub-section, entitled "Mus Course," following Series II. These later materials have been relocated and now precede the 1944-1964 materials in order to maintain reverse-chronological order throughout the collection. These two distinct chronological groupings have been maintained within Subseries B and their titles reflect those which appeared on the original file drawer divider labels. This rearrangement is intended to facilitate use by researchers.
  A notable gap exists in the Museum Course records in this collection from 1963 to 1971. Many of these 'missing' records (1963-1968) may be found in the John Coolidge and Agnes Mongan director's files, also held by the Harvard Art Museum Archives.
  - Museum Course Curriculum Review, A.
    - Answers from Museum Course Students, 1954, 1.
    - Museum Course - Suggestions for 1953-1954, 2.
    - Museum Training 1947-1950 [1946-1950], 3.
      [Note: Folders 3-6 contain the opinions of many prominent museum directors, staff and academics regarding the essential components of a museum training curriculum]
    - Museum Training - For Files on Reports, etc. See Dr. Kuhn [1950, n.d.], 4.
    - Museum Training - Replies to Form Letters [1950], 5-6.
    - Museum Training - Answers to Replies [1948, 1950], 7.
  - Museum Course & Teaching Materials, B.
    - Mus Course [1965-1981]
      - Art Museum Problems [1975-1976, 1980-1981], 8.
        [Note: Some materials in this folder are RESTRICTED; access requires the written permission of the Curator of the Harvard Art Museum Archives]
      - Mus Course First Ex. [1975], 9.
      - Mus Course Dupes etc. [1975?], 10.
      - Mus. Course 74/79 [1974?], 11.
      - Mus Course - Unused [1972?], 12.
      - Mus. Course Outlines etc. [1971-1972], 13.
      - Hartford FA101 [1971?], 14.
        [Note: item removed to oversize cabinet]
      - 101 Installation [n.d.], 15.
      - MFA [Museum of Fine Arts, Boston] Museum Course Introduction [1971?], 16.
      - MFA [Museum of Fine Arts, Boston] 101 [1971], 17.
      - 101 Curators [n.d.], 18.
      - Introduction to Museums Exercise [n.d.], 19.
        [Note: contains only one document]
      - Fogg [n.d.], 20.
      - 101 Budget [1971?], 21.
      - 101 Piloa [Pilon fountain] [n.d.], 22.
      - 101 Membership [1971], 23.
      - Mus. Course Introd. [n.d.], 24.
      - 101 - Education [of Museumgoers] [n.d.], 25.
      - Rogier [van der Weyden] St. Luke [Lecture Notes] [n.d.], 26.
      - Museum Course [1965, n.d.], 27.
      - MFA [Museum of Fine Arts, Boston] Finances -- Analyses JC [n.d.], 28.
        [Note: contains only two documents]
        [Note: Contents of this folder are RESTRICTED; access requires the written permission of the Curator of the Harvard Art Museum Archives]
      - MFA [Museum of Fine Arts, Boston] Mus Course - Outlines etc. [empty] [n.d.], 29.
      - 101: 4th Acquisitions [n.d.], 30.
      - Connoisseurship [n.d.], 31.
    - Fine Arts 201, 1949-1962 [1944-1964]
      - New York Trip: Jan. 5-7, 1962; FA201 [1961-1962, 1964], 32.
      - FA201 Spring Trip Apr. 2-6, 1963 -- Wash., Balti., & Philly, 33.
      - Museum Course 1961-1962, 34-35.
        [Note: Some materials in these folders are RESTRICTED; access requires the written permission of the Curator of the Harvard Art Museum Archives]
      - Trip April 1962, Philadelphia and Washington [1961-1962], 36.
      - 2nd Lecture Museum Course [n.d.], 37.
      - FA201: Fogg Budget, 1960-1962, 38.
      - FA201 Mimeogr. Mat. 1959-1962, 39.
      - FA201 Expenses of Museum 1961 [1960-1961], 40.
      - Museum Course Trips to Wash. & Phil, April 8, 1961 [1960-1961], 41-42.
      - FA201 1960-1961 General, 43-44.
        [Note: Some materials in folder 43 are RESTRICTED; access requires the written permission of the Curator of the Harvard Art Museum Archives]
      - FA201 1960-1961 Mimeogr. Material, 45.
      - New York Trip: FA201; Nov. 11-12, 1960, 46.
      - FA201 Spring Trip [1959-1960], 47.
      - Museum Course 1959-1960, 48.
      - Mus. Course 1959-1960 -- Mimeographical Material, 49.
      - Mus. Course 1959-1960, 50.
      - Fine Arts 201 - 1959-1960, 51.
      - New York Trip, FA201 -- Nov. 14-15, 1959, 52.
      - FA201/General; Museum Course 1958-1959, 53-54.
        [Note: Some materials in folder 53 are RESTRICTED; access requires the written permission of the Curator of the Harvard Art Museum Archives]
      - FA201 Mimeogr. Material 1958-1959, 55.
      - N.Y. Dec. 13 & 14, 1958, 56.
      - Museum Course 1958, 57.
      - Museum Course 1957-1958 [1956-1958], 58.
      - FA201, Museum Course 1956-1957 -- General, 59.
      - FA201, Museum Course 1956-1957 -- Mimeographical Material, 60.
      - Museum Course 201 - Spring 1956-1957, 61-62.
      - FA201, 1955-1956 Mimeographed Mat. [1955-1957], 63.
      - Museum Course, 1955-1956 [1954-1956], 64.
      - FA201 Trip to Phila., April 1955, 65.
      - Museum Course 1954-1955 - General [1953-1955], 66.
      - Museum Course - Mimeo Forms 1953-1954 [1953-1955], 67.
      - Fine Arts 201 General - 1953-1954, 68-69.
      - FA201 Apprenticeships 1953-1954, 70.
      - Museum Course Trip to Phila., Balt., & Wash., April 7, 8, 9, 1954 [1953-1954], 71.
      - Fine Arts 201 - 1951-1952, 72-73.
        [Note: Some materials in folder 73 are RESTRICTED; access requires the written permission of the Curator of the Harvard Art Museum Archives]
      - Museum Course - Mimeograph Papers -- 1951-1952 [1950-1952], 74.
      - Museum Course 1949-1950 [1944, 1946, 1948-1952], 75-76.
        [Note: item removed from folder 75 to oversize cabinet]
      - Fine Arts 201 (Museum Course) -- 1950-1951, 77.
- Speeches, II.
  This series is comprised of handwritten and typescript speeches delivered to the museum's Board of Overseers-appointed Visiting Committee, between 1948 and 1958. Other files related to the Visiting Committee are located in the John Coolidge and Agnes Mongan director's files, also held by the Harvard Art Museum Archives.
  - Speech: Visiting Committee, Dec. 8, 1958, 78.
  - Speech for Visiting Committee -- Dec. 2, 1957, 79.
  - Speech Visit. Com. Dec. 2, 1957 -- Painting Collections, 80.
  - Speech - OVC [Overseers Visiting Committee], April 22, 1957, 81.
  - Speech to Visit. Com. - Dec. 3, 1956, 82.
  - Speech to Visit. Com. - Dec. 5, 1955, 83.
  - Speech to Visit. Com. - Dec. 6, 1954, 84.
  - Speech to Visiting Committee - Dec. 7, 1953, 85.
  - Speech to Overseers Feb. 2, 1953, Y.C., 86.
  - Speech Overseers Visiting Comm. -- Dec-51 [1951], 87.
  - Policy Report [to the Overseers Visiting Committee] [1950-1951?], 88-89.
  - Speech Given Right After J.C. Got Directorship [1948, 1951], 90.
  - Speech Overseers Visiting Comm. -- October, 1950, 91.
    [Note: contains audograph disc]
  - Financial Outlook for the Fogg 1948 [1950?], 92.
  - Speech to Overseers Visiting Comm. -- Dec-49 [1949], 93.
  - Draft for Chairman's Report to Overseers for 1949 [1948-1949], 94.
  - Speech to Overseers Visiting Comm. -- November 1948 and June, 1948 [1948], 95.
  - Speeches to Overseers May 1948, 96.
  - Proposals for Fogg, 1947 [1948?], 97.
  - Princeton Bicentennial [Speech] [1946-1947], 98.
- Personal Papers, III.
  Series III encompasses Coolidge's personal papers, including correspondence related to his first published book, Mill and Mansion, his membership in various organizations and his involvement in scholarly research projects. Much of Coolidge's personal correspondence consists of requests for publications which he hoped to add to his collection, congratulatory notes sent to other scholars on their publications and similar letters received commending Coolidge's published works and achievements. In addition, there are a number of requests from publications desiring submissions from Coolidge, and individuals hoping that Coolidge would speak at their institution or event. Coolidge was frequently asked for advice regarding professional appointments, museum administration, gallery planning and the establishment of graduate training programs in the fields of art history, architectural history and museum studies. He served on a number of boards and committees related to museums, academic institutions and scholarly publications and organizations, and the series includes many official letters of appointment to these positions. Some of the correspondence in this series concerns Coolidge's finances and acknowledgments for charitable contributions and tax-related information. Other correspondence concerns Coolidge's family, particularly his daughter, Mary-Elizabeth "Penny" Coolidge Warren, and his mother, Theresa Reynolds Coolidge.
  Series III was found in notable disarray. The personal papers from 1947 to 1963 were filed in chronological order while those from 1970 to 1967 inexplicably reverted to a reverse chronological arrangement. Some re-arrangement was therefore necessary to maintain the predominant reverse chronological order of the collection. Wherever possible, original order was maintained. In addition, previously devised organizational categories, (indicated by the existence of labeled file drawer dividers), including, "Personal," "Fogg," "Writings," "Organizations" and "Projects," often had no correlation to the files which followed them. Despite this disorganization, the categories proved applicable to the papers found in the series. With this in mind, correspondence, such as that related to the publication of Mill and Mansion (which had been filed incongruously both in time and place), was moved to the "Writings" section. Similarly, a group of records related to professional organizations, such as, the Society of Architectural Historians and the Art Historians Dining Club have been re-filed under "Organizations." In each of these instances a discernable cluster of files relating to one of the fore mentioned categories seemed simply to have been misfiled.
  - Personal Correspondence, A.
    - [Dolores] Hayden[1971, 1975], 99.
    - Letters Answered or Needing No Answer [1971], 100.
    - Letters 1970/1971, 101.
    - [Roger A.] Kindler [Assignment for Fine Arts 52] [1970], 102.
    - Letters 1969/1970, 103-105.
    - Letters 1969/1970, 106-108.
      [Note: Some materials in folder 108 are RESTRICTED; access requires the written permission of the Curator of the Harvard Art Museum Archives]
    - Economist [news clippings] [1968], 109.
    - J.C. Personal Retirement Letters [1968], 110-112.
    - Teaching [Course ideas for teaching after retirement as museum director] [1968], 113.
    - Future [Notes regarding possible areas of study and teaching] [ca.1968], 114.
    - Loring Wolcott[1968], 115.